so now let's look at processor pipeline
stalls and how they can happen let's say
we have a five-stage Pipeline and this
is where we fetch the instruction then
we decode it and read registers then we
use the ALU to compute the result of the
instruction then we Access Memory if
this is a load or store instruction and
then we write the result of the
instruction to a register this is what
happens in Cycle One cycle 2 cycle 3 Etc
suppose we have a load instruction here
here in our Pipeline and it's going to
load into R1 something from memory while
this load is in the ear stage here
Computing the address so it hasn't
accessed memory yet suppose we have an
add instruction that needs to use the R1
and this instruction is already reading
registers here so that it can compute
the result in the next stage and we have
a subsequent instruction here let's say
another ad that adds R2 to one and
produces R3
so now the problem is that this ad here
is reading the wrong value of the
register so if we let it proceed further
because in the next cycle this load will
be here and now it's actually accessing
memory but by then it's too late this
add If It Moves here will use the value
of
R1 that is the wrong one it's the value
of the R1 before the load actually
produced the value and this is where we
get a processor store all pretty much
what needs to happen is the ad needs to
stay here until it gets the correct
value of R1 from the load because the ad
is stuck here the next instruction also
needs to stay where it is because it
cannot move here that means that in our
pipeline now we have a bubble just like
we did in the production line we can
have more than one bubble because of a
single dependence between instructions
so in this example next cycle the load
has loaded the value from memory into R1
and is now writing that value to a
register the add needs to repeat the
read of R1 because in this cycle here it
still didn't get the correct value of R1
although the load was now loading that
value from memory the R1 was not written
yet so now the load is writing the add
repeats the
read and because the ad is still here
the next instruction is still stuck here
and that means that we have two cycles
worth of stall in this cycle it could be
that for example the load is writing to
R1 in the first half of the cycle and
this ad is reading R1 in the second half
of the cycle so next cycle the ad can
move on but it could be that the load
actually takes a full cycle to write the
result in which case we will have
another cycle of stalling so let's
suppose that we can do this that we can
write R1 and then read it in the same
cycle if that is the case then next
cycle which is cycle 4 we will have the
load leaves the pipeline the pipeline
bubble here moves forward in the
pipeline this pipeline bubble moves
forward in the pipeline and now the ad
finally moves on so the next instruction
after this add can move on we can fetch
a next instruction and so on so as you
can see here a processor pipeline stall
creates a problem because normally every
cycle after the load leaves every cycle
we would have the next instruction leave
but in this case after the load leaves
there are two cycles worth of pipeline
bubble that finish before the next
instruction so really instead of just
having one cycle for the load one cycle
for the ad and so on to finish we now
have one cycle for the load two cycles
worth of not finishing anything and then
the ad and so on and that causes our
pipeline to have a CPI of more than
one if we count these three instructions
one to three instructions will finish
over five Cycles three cycles for them
and two cycles for the bubble so really
our CPI is significantly larger than one
a processor pipeline may also need to be
flushed this is an example that we
didn't have in our car assembly line